Now that you know how to import data to data frames
现在你已了解如何将数据导入 dataframe
and use the most essential methods, let's wrangle some data.
同时学会了基本的方法 现在我们开始处理一些数据吧
We may use the same music streaming service log data set we used previously.
我们会用到之前的音乐云服务日志数据集
So let's just get started.
开始吧
First, let me import a few things here from pyspark.
首先 从 pyspark 导入这些
I already typed these in.
我已经导入好了
We will need a few functions as well as types for our calculations later.
稍后会用到这些函数和类型来进行计算
I also imported date time as well as Numpy and pandas.
我还导入了 datetime 以及 Numpy 和 pandas
Let's load our input data set from HDFS as well.
现在我们从 HDFS 中载入数据集
We will use the sparky file looks more than JSON file,
用 sparky 读取 JSON 格式的方法读取 JSON 文件
and read it into the user log data frame.
并将 dataframe 存入 user_log 这个变量中
Let's take a look at the first five records.
我们先看前五个记录
As we saw it earlier,
正如我们之前看到的
Kenneth is listening to a "Showaddywaddy" song.
kenneth 正在听一首 “ Showaddywaddy ” 的歌
The records are a bit hard to read.
记录有点难以阅读
So as a reminder, let's print the schema,
我们可以把框架打印出来
so we can see the columns we have in this data frame.
这样我们可以看到dataframe 的所有列名了
We can also call described on the whole frame to see the count,
我们也可以对整个 dataframe 用 describe 方法来查看每列的计数
mean, standard deviation, min and max values of each column.
平均值 标准差 最小值和最大值
Previously when we used this method,
之前 我们使用这种方法时
we only saw the column names.
我们只看到了列名
If we had to show, we will see the actual statistics.
如果在后面加个 show 我们将看到实际的统计数据
This is still a bit hard to read as is.
这有点难读
So we can just take a look at individual columns.
所以我们可以按列挨个看
For example, describing the artist field,
例如 描述 artist 字段
give us these stats.
会得到这些统计数据
Not sure about mean and standard deviation.
暂时较难看出平均值和标准差
Means in this particular case.
在这个例子中的含义
If we select a column with the numeric type,
如果选择一个数值类型的列
we will see more meaningful values.
我们会看到更有意义的值
So as you can see,
可以看出
we have 10,000 of the session IDs.
我们有 10000 个 session ID
The values are between 9-7,144,
值在 9 - 7144 之间
and we have some mean and standard deviation here.
这里也有平均值和标准差
To check how many rows we have in the data frame,
要查看 dataframe 中共有多少行
we can just use the count method.
可以用 count 方法
We have 10,000 rows here.
这里一共有 10000 行
So, by session ID,
所以 所有的记录都有 session ID
has a value for all of our records,
而并不是所有的记录
the artist field, that currently doesn't.
都有 artist 字段
This make sense, since if the record
这是有道理的
doesn't refer to playing a song,
因为如果记录首先应该指的是播放歌曲的记录
we should not have any artist.
而不是应该是 artist 记录
Let's see what sort of page requests do we have,
接下来让我们看看请求的页面有哪些
by looking at the page field.
通过查看page字段
Using drop duplicates, just means
使用 drop duplicates
that we will see each kind once,
这样每个页面只会出现一次了
and sort code on the page field again.
并根据页面字段进行排序
Just sorts these different options alphabetically.
按字母顺序进行排序
Users can log in and out.
用户可以登录和退出
They might visit the homepage,
他们可能会访问主页
that just home here or play a song.
这里是主页 或播放一首歌
Later we will focus on users who chose
稍后我们会聚焦那些
to downgrade their paid account to a free one.
将付费帐户降级为免费帐户的用户
So let's make comment on that of the submit downgrades field.
那么 submit downgrades 字段里会有一些评论
We can get the events associated with a particular user ID
我们可以通过筛选特定用户 ID
by filtering for a particular value.
获取其相关事件
Let's pick a few columns and the user ID and collect all the events.
让我们选择几个列名以及用户 ID 然后并收集其所有事件
As we see here, user Kenneth was listening to a few songs,
正如我们在这里看到的 用户 Kenneth 听了几首歌
visited the homepage, and then listened to a few more songs here.
访问了主页 然后在这里又听了几首歌
So this is how a typical user event log might look like.
这就是一个典型的用户事件日志的样子
Let's say that we are interested in
现在我们对
how many songs users are listening to in a particular hour.
用户在特定小时内听歌数量很感兴趣
To compute this, first we need to convert
要计算这个 首先我们需要把
the timestamps to date time from epoch time,
时间戳从 epoch time 格式 转换为 datetime 格式
so we can get the hour of the day.
这样我们才能获取时间里的具体小时数字
To do this, we will define a user-defined function called get hour.
为此 我们将定义一个名为 get hour 的自定义函数
Using get hour, we can add a new column called hour to our data frame.
使用get hour 我们可以在 dataframe 添加一个名为 hour 的新列
Since Spark lazy evaluation,
因为 Spark 采用惰性评估
nothing happened so far.
目前为止它还没做任何事
But if we take a look at the head,
但是如果我们使用 head 方法
the hour value will be computed,
小时值就会被计算出来
at least for this first record.
至少第一个记录的值会计算出来
So this particular song was played at 10:00 PM.
这首歌是晚上10点播放的
The next step is to count the next song page request,
下一步是计算一天中不同小时的
group by the hour we just computed.
歌曲页面请求数
Let's also order the result,
我们把结果排个序
so we get the hours of the day in order.
这样一天的时间就按顺序排列了
We also need to add show other advisors statement when we evaluated.
接下来我们还需要加上 show 方法来查看统计结果
To visualize these results,
接下来我们要把结果可视化
we can turn this small Spark data frame into
我们可以把这个小 Spark dataframe 转换为
a Pandas data frame and use matplotlib to plot a graph.
Pandas dataframe 并使用 matplotlib 绘制图形
We can make our graph a little bit prettier.
我们还可以让图表更漂亮一点
We can certainly see some trends in
从图中 我们可以看到
how many songs our users played in different hours of the day.
用户在一天中的不同时段播放歌曲的趋势
Before we continue to compute any other aggregates on the data frame,
在继续汇总 dataframe 里的其他数据前
let's make sure that we don't have any missing values.
我们要先确保 dataframe 中没有任何缺失值
As we saw earlier, some of the fields are meant to be none,
正如我们之前看到的 一些字段里就应该是空值
but we would like to make sure that we have,
但我们要确保
for example the user ID and the session ID for all the records.
例如 所有记录的用户ID和 sessionid 都不为空
With the drop-any method,
使用 drop any 方法
we can drop all the records that have none in either of these fields.
我们可以删除这些字段中为空的记录
If we count our rules again,
如果再次对行计数
we will see that we haven't list any records.
我们会发现我们没有删除任何一行
So let's take a look at the user IDs.
那么让我们来看看用户ID
There is no none value in the user ID column.
用户ID列中没有空值
There is certainly one suspicious here, an empty string.
这里有一个可疑的值 一个空字符串
Let's just filter out all the rows that has
我们把用户ID为
this empty string value as the user ID.
空字符串的行都过滤掉
If we count our rows again,
如果我们再次计算行数
we will see that we lost about 340 records.
会看到我们删除了大约340条记录
So this way, we made sure that they
这样 我们就确保了
only include user IDs that have a valid value.
所有用户 ID 值都是有效的
In our computation, we might want to distinguish
在我们的计算中 我们可能需要区分
a user's activity before and after a particular event,
用户在特定事件前后的行为数据
for example, before and after they have
例如 区分用户
downgraded their account from a paid one to free one.
把帐户从付费帐户降级为免费帐户前后的活动
Let's find the user who downgraded their service first.
让我们先把降级服务的用户找出来
Apparently, user ID 1138,
显然 用户 ID 1138
a user called Kelly downgraded her service.
一位名叫凯利的用户降级了她的服务
So let's just list her user activity.
那我们把她的用户活动列出来
Let's also include the level column.
同时我们把她的用户级别字段也包括进来
So now we can see that she was listening
可以看到一开始她
to some songs still using the paid service.
在使用付费服务来听歌的
After a while, she submitted this downgrade
过了一段时间 她降级了服务
and she became a free user.
成了一名免费用户
Our final goal is to create a new column
我们最终目标是新建一个字段
which divides the events of a particular user,
它会基于特殊的事件
based on these special events.
使用不同值来区分是事件前还是事件后
Let's call this column phase.
我们称这个字段为 phase
So, user inventory should have a different value in
用户 phase 字段里
the phase column before and after she downgraded her service.
在降级服务前后的值会不一样
To get phase, first we need to flag
要创建 phase 首先我们把
the records that refer to this special event,
关于特殊事件的记录标记出来
in our case, downgrading the service.
在我们的案例中 这个特殊事件就是降级服务
So let's create a column called downgraded first.
我们先创建一个名为 downgrade 的字段
The values here will be one,
如果该事件指的是 降级服务
if the event refers to a downgrade, and zero otherwise.
那字段里的值就是 1 否则为 0
So I just defined this function flag downgrade event.
好啦 我刚刚定义了这个函数 flag_downgrade_event
That returns an integer either one or zero,
函数会根据事件是否是 提交降级
depending on if the event was a submit downgrade.
返回整数 1 或 0
If we take a look at the head of user log valid,
如果我们看一下 user_log_valid 的第一行
we can see that the column downgraded appeared,
我们可以看到 downgrade 字段出现了
and in this particular case it's very easy.
这行中 它的值为 0
To compute phase, we can use a trick.
要计算 phase 我们可以使用一个小技巧
If we sort our records for a particular user in reverse time order,
如果按逆时间顺序对特定用户的记录进行排序
and add up the values in the downgraded column up onto the particular role,
并对降级列中的值依此求和 直到发生特定事件那行
we can use that as phase,
我们可以用它作为 phase
and we will achieve exactly what we wanted to do.
这完全满足我们的要求
You can find an illustration after these videos to see why this actually work.
你可以在这节视频后找到更多原理解释
We can use a window function to compute this cumulative sums using
我们先把行按逆时间顺序排列
all preceding rows in reverse chronological order, okay?
然后使用窗口函数把特定行之前的数据加总
So I forgot to import window.
我忘了导入窗口函数了
Let's do it first.
那我们先导入函数
So now I define this window function, where we partition,
现在我定义这么一个窗口函数 然后我们根据
or you can think of it as a group by as well,
用户ID 来分组
by the user ID, order arguments in a descending time order,
按逆时间顺序排序
and take into account all previous rows,
加总降级行之上的所有行
but no rows afterwards.
降级行之下的行都不加总
Now we can, using this window function,
现在我们就可以用这个窗口函数
actually compute the phase column.
来计算 phase 字段了
Let's select Kelly's events again.
让我们再次选择 kelly 的活动
I just added timestamp and the phase columns.
我添加了时间戳和 phase 字段
Let's sort this data frame by timestamp.
让我们按时间戳对这个 dataframe 进行排序
Now if it we take a look at the records,
现在如果我们看一下记录
all the events before the downgrade event
降级事件之上的所有事件
belong to phase one, like this.
的 phase 字段的值都变成了 1
If we scroll down,
如果我们向下滚动
we will see that after the submit downgrade,
提交降级这个事件下面的行
we switched to phase zero.
的 phase 字段都变成了 0
If we had more than one phase,
如果我们有多个降级事件
we will see the phase values decreasing from n to zero.
我们将看到 phase 值从n减小到零